Respected judges and dear classmates, hello everyone!
尊敬的评委老师，亲爱的同学们，大家好！
Our project is
我们的项目是
a non-intrusive power load classification
基于深度学习算法的
and prediction system based on deep learning algorithms.
非入侵式电力负载分类与预测系统
Next, I will provide a detailed explanation of our project.
接下来，我将为大家详细讲解我们的项目
Our team divided tasks rationally
我们小组合理分工
and collaboratively completed this project.
共同完成了这个项目
I will introduce the system from the following aspects.
我将从以下几个方面对系统进行介绍
First, let’s talk about the motivation behind the design.
首先，让我们来谈谈设计动机
Non-intrusive load monitoring (NILM) methods refer to
非入侵式电力负载分类与预测方法是指
analyzing overall electricity usage data
通过分析总用电数据
without monitoring specific devices,
无需监测具体设备
to infer and predict the electricity consumption of individual appliances.
即可推断并预测各个电器用电情况
As shown on the right,
如右图所示
the system does not require sensors to be installed
系统不在每个电器的电源线上
on each appliance’s power line.
安装传感器
Instead, it analyzes household electricity data
而是通过分析入户总用电数据
to estimate the usage of each device
来推测各设备的使用情况
and predict the total power consumption in the near future.
以及预测未来短时间内的总功耗
So, why is this technology necessary?
那么，为什么需要这样的技术呢？
Investigations by national authorities reveal that
国家权威机构调查发现
both in China and globally,
在我国乃至全世界
standby and unnecessary power consumption
因待机等非必要耗电
are increasingly leading to electricity waste.
造成电力资源浪费的现象日益严重
Moreover, with the rise of smart grid technology,
另外，随着智能电网技术的兴起
cost-effective non-intrusive detection systems
经济高效的非入侵式检测系统
meet the needs of both electricity users and suppliers.
可满足广大用电与供电单位的需求
Additionally, non-intrusive systems
并且，非入侵式系统
do not require complex sensor hardware support,
不需要繁杂的传感器硬件支撑
making them low-cost, highly reliable,
因而它成本低廉、可靠性高
and easily acceptable to users.
易被用户接受
This technology also has numerous advantages,
这项技术还有诸多优势
which, due to time constraints,
由于时间原因
I won’t elaborate on here.
不在此一一讲解
Furthermore, the computational power for our system
另外我们所研发系统的算力
is provided by the National Supercomputing Sunway Platform,
来自国家超算山河计算平台
in response to the government’s call to vigorously develop the digital economy.
响应了政府大力发展数字经济的号召
It is a vivid example of bringing computing power
是让算力走进千家万户
to households and empowering various industries.
赋能千行百业的生动体现
In summary, whether for ordinary households or industrial factories,
总而言之，无论是普通家庭还是企业工厂
there is an urgent need for an intelligent system and algorithm
都亟需一套智能算法和系统
to monitor the real-time operational status of appliances,
来监控电器的实时运行状态
identify unnecessary power consumption,
识别不必要的电力消耗
and help save energy
这不仅有助于节约能源
and reduce electricity costs.
还能降低用电成本
The system should also be capable of predicting short-term electricity consumption,
系统还应具备预测短期电能消耗的能力
enabling companies to plan their electricity usage more scientifically.
使企业能够更加科学地规划电力的使用
This is especially important under a tiered electricity pricing mechanism.
特别是实行阶梯电价机制的情况
For this purpose, our system
为此，我们的系统
mainly includes classification and prediction functionalities.
主要包含分类与预测的功能
The classification function
其中分类功能
can inform users in real time
可实时告知用户
about the operational status of each appliance.
各电器设备的运作状态
The prediction function can estimate
预测功能则能预估
users' short-term future electricity consumption.
用户未来短时间内的电能消耗情况
Second, algorithm design.
第二，算法设计
Our system adopts a cascaded model architecture,
我们的系统采用了级联模型架构
which includes a classification module
分别包括分类分解模块
and a numerical prediction module.
和数值预测模块
Input data
输入数据
is first processed with the classification module for labeling,
首先通过分类模块进行标签化处理
after which
随后
the data and its labels are input into the numerical prediction module
数据及其标签被输入至数值预测模块
to generate the final power prediction value.
以生成最终的功率预测值
Next, I will introduce them individually.
下面，我将分别进行介绍
Here is the classification model diagram.
这是分类模型示意图
First, the input data undergoes windowing processing.
首先，将输入的数据加窗处理
Then, power values are grouped.
再将功率数值进行分组
Next, the number of samples
接着，统计每个时间窗内
falling into each group is counted for each time window,
落入各组的样本数量
yielding a frequency distribution.
得到频数分布
To obtain feature vectors,
为了得到特征向量
we normalize the frequency of each time window
我们对每个时间窗的频数
by dividing by the window length.
进行归一化处理
Finally, we use a fully connected neural network
即除以窗长
to input a matrix composed of the feature vectors from the time windows
最后，我们采用全连接神经网络
and output the one-hot encoding of the corresponding appliance category.
输入由时间窗特征向量组成的矩阵
During these computations,
上述计算过程中
we adopted shorter window lengths
我们采用了较短的窗长
and more power value groups.
以及较多组的功率数值
According to Dirichlet's principle,
根据迪利克雷原理
only a few samples will fall into certain groups,
将会有很少的样本落入某个分组中
resulting in a very sparse feature matrix
因而特征矩阵将会非常稀疏
that cannot be directly input into a neural network.
无法直接输入神经网络
It needs to be compressed using the principal component analysis (PCA) algorithm.
需要经过主成分分析算法的压缩处理
The algorithm retains 96% of the variance,
算法保留了96%的方差
effectively compressing 660-dimensional features into 17 dimensions,
将660个维度的特征有效压缩为了17维
transforming the feature matrix into a dense matrix.
使特征矩阵成为了密集矩阵
When selecting the model,
选用模型时
we compared the performance of a fully connected network and GRU
我们对比了全连接网络与GRU
(Gated Recurrent Unit).
（门控循环单元）的性能
After tuning the hyperparameters,
经过超参数的调整
both achieved maximum accuracies of 91% and 90%,
两者分别可达到91%和90%的最高准确率
However, the testing phase revealed
但是上线测试说明
that GRU, due to its need to attend to multiple time windows,
GRU由于要关注其他时间窗
consumes significantly more inference power than fully connected networks.
其推理功耗明显大于全连接网络
Thus, we opted for the latter.
故我们选择后者
Next, I will elaborate on the power prediction model.
我再来讲一下功率预测模型
The right diagram shows power waveforms
右图展示了同一电器
of the same appliance across different time spans.
不同时间跨度下的功率波形
Data exhibits strong patterns on a macro scale,
数据在宏观上极具规律性
yet appears entirely erratic on a micro scale.
而微观上却毫无规律可言
This is due to numerous external uncertainties,
正是外部诸多的不确定因素
which pose challenges for short-term power prediction.
为短时功率预测带来了挑战
To address this problem,
为了解决这一难题
we designed the following model architecture.
我们设计了如下模型结构
During data processing,
在处理数据时
the data is first segmented into frames.
首先对数据进行分帧处理
Each data frame is then divided into time windows.
然后在每个数据帧内进行分窗
A feature vector is calculated for each time window.
每个时间窗都会计算出一个特征向量
Multiple time window feature vectors
多个时间窗的特征向量
form a feature matrix.
组成一个特征矩阵
These feature vectors
这些特征向量
comprise transient features with high variability
由波动大的暂态特征
and steady-state features that are more stable.
和不易变的稳态特征两部分组成
Transient features are extracted using Fast Fourier Transform (FFT),
暂态特征通过快速傅里叶变换
yielding amplitudes and phases corresponding to frequency indices.
得到各频率序数对应的振幅和相位
According to electrical theory,
而根据电学相关理论
steady-state features consist of maximum, minimum, arithmetic mean,
稳态特征由最大值、最小值、算术平均值
RMS energy,
能量有效值
and crest factor, among others.
波峰系数等构成
Additionally, the model uses an Embedding layer
此外模型通过Embedding层
to map discrete appliance types into continuous embedding vectors,
将离散的电器种类映射为连续的嵌入向量
which form an integral part of the steady-state features.
作为稳态特征的重要组成部分
Inspired by generative language models,
受生成式语言模型的启发
the feature matrix is treated as a "word embedding matrix."
特征矩阵被视为“词嵌入矩阵"
Using six layers of Transformer Blocks
通过6层Transformer Block
and subsequent attention pooling,
和后续的注意力平均化处理
a prediction vector is generated.
生成预测向量
Finally, inverse FFT is applied
最后通过逆FFT
to transform the frequency-domain vector
将暂态特征中
of transient features back into time-series data,
频域向量部分，转化为时间序列
completing the prediction process.
从而完成预测
Due to time constraints,
由于时间原因
the equations and detailed calculations will not be elaborated here.
公式和具体计算过程不再过多阐述
Please refer to the accompanying documentation and PPT for details.
请老师们在文档和PPT中查阅参考
As shown on the left, initial experimental results were less than ideal.
如左图，实验结果最初并不尽如人意
The root cause
究其原因
was that the Transformer did not account for relationships
是Transformer不会关注一个时间步
between internal features and feature dimensions at individual timesteps.
内部特征和特征各维度之间的关系
Adding fully connected layers
而添加全连接网络
effectively resolved this issue.
则可以很好地解决这个问题
This is the performance of our improved model
这是我们经过改进后的模型
on the test dataset.
在测试集上的效果
As seen, the predictive capability of the enhanced model improved significantly.
可以看到，改进后的模型预测能力显著提高
Next, I will demonstrate the project in action.
下面我将进行项目的演示
Part 3: Project Deployment
第三部分，项目部署
The system adopts a "distributed application, centralized computation"
系统采用了“应用分布，算力集中”的
cloud-based collaborative architecture.
云端协同架构
The database serves as the "hub" of the system.
数据库是系统的“枢纽”
AI models are deployed in the compute network,
AI模型部署于算力网络
and smart meters act as edge devices.
电能表为边缘设备
The backend is distributed across neighborhoods or factories.
后端则分布于各小区或工厂
The design of the message queue (MQ)
MQ的设计
alleviates the surge of requests from the distributed backend,
削弱了来自分布式后端的请求洪峰
reduces the pressure on the GPU clusters,
减轻了GPU集群的压力
and enhances the overall system performance.
提升了系统的整体性能
This design is low-coupling and highly scalable,
这种设计耦合度低，且易于扩展
aligning with modern software system design principles.
符合现代化软件系统的设计模式
During development,
项目开发时
we used NVIDIA A100 GPUs
我们使用了英伟达 A100 GPU
and Intel's 2nd Gen Neural Compute Sticks among other hardware devices.
和英特尔第2代神经计算棒等硬件设备
The runtime environment is based on the Shanhe Supercomputing Platform
项目的运行环境则基于山河超算平台
and includes SQLite, WeChat Mini Program, PyTorch, the C++ toolchain,
以及SQLite、微信小程序、PyTorch、C++工具链
and RabbitMQ among other software.
以及Rabbit MQ等软件
Here, you can see the interface of our WeChat Mini Program client.
现在展示的，是我们微信小程序客户端的界面
We primarily used the WeChat Developer Tools
我们主要使用了微信开发者工具
for front-end development.
进行前端开发
For waveform plotting, we utilized the line chart components provided by the ECharts library.
波形绘制，使用了ECharts库中提供的折线图组件
The backend program is built using the C++17 standard Web Server,
后端程序使用C++17标准构建的Web Server
based on a single-reactor multi-threaded architecture.
基于单Reactor多线程架构
The system core comprises modules for logging, thread pool management,
系统核心由日志记录、线程池管理
IO multiplexing, HTTP handling,
IO多路复用、HTTP处理
buffer management, and blocking queue management.
缓冲区管理和阻塞队列等模块组成
HTTP request messages are read using a scatter-read approach
HTTP请求报文通过分散读方式读入
and efficiently parsed
并利用有限状态机
using finite state machines and regular expressions.
与正则表达式进行高效解析
Finally, we conclude with a project summary.
最后是项目总结
Time flies, and months have passed.
白驹过隙，时光荏苒
Looking back on these months,
回眸数月时光
under the careful guidance of Professors Jia Ruixiang and Chen Jing,
在贾瑞祥老师和陈静老师的悉心指导下
the five of us worked diligently together,
我们五人通力合作
learning through competition,
以赛促学
and gaining valuable insights.
收获颇丰
We finally developed this large-scale system.
终于研发出了这个规模不小的系统
With that, our project presentation concludes.
至此，我们的项目汇报完毕
We sincerely thank the judges for listening and providing feedback.
衷心感谢各位评委老师的倾听和指教